Guide to the J. Walter Thompson Company. Legal Department Records, 1936-1979
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company. Legal Department records 1936-1979
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company.
10.6 linear feet Extent: 7900 Items
Founded in 1864, the J. Walter Thompson Company (JWT) is one of the largest and oldest enduring advertising agencies in the United States. The J. Walter Thompson Company (JWT) Legal Department Records contain releases for models and photographers associated with JWT campaigns between 1936-1979, and especially the 1950s. The collection also contains publications associated with JWT clients which required model releases. Companies represented in the collection include Ford, Gillette, Kodak, Lever Brothers, Pacific Mills (Cocheco Manufacturing Company), Pan American World Airways, Quaker Oats, Radio Corporation of America (RCA), Seven-Up, Singer, and Uncle Ben's. Photographers mentioned or whose work appears in the collection include Richard Avedon, Ralph Bartholomew, Anton Bruehl, Horst, Otto Mayo, Valentino Sarra, and Francesco Scavullo. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
RL.00721
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
However, materials may not be photocopied.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The J. Walter Thompson Legal Department Records, were pulled from storage by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library in 1986.
Collection Overview
The JWT Legal Department Records date from 1936-1979, with the majority of materials dating from the 1950s. The collection primarily contains release forms, photographs and publications associated with JWT campaigns. The collection also contains routine legal contracts which list the terms of agreement between the client, talent and the J. Walter Thompson Company. Companies represented in the collection include Ford, Gillette, Kodak, Lever Brothers, Pacific Mills (Cocheco Manufacturing Company), Pan American, Quaker Oats, Radio Corporation of America (RCA), Seven-Up, Singer, and Uncle Ben's. Photographers mentioned or whose work appears in the collection include Richard Avedon, Ralph Bartholomew, Anton Bruehl, Horst, Otto Mayo, Valentino Sarra, and Francesco Scavullo.
Collection Arrangement
The collection is divided into six series: Model Releases, Photographers, Publications, Reports, Model-Client-Date Cards, and Overscale Talent Releases. The Model Releases Series and the Photographers Series contain photographs and photostats of models as they often appeared in an advertisement. Attached to the visual is a signed release by the model specifying the length of the contract, the client and the date. The Publications Series contains an assortment of publications requiring model releases, and especially Ford newsletters from the 1950s. The Reports Series consists of contour sheets for Pacific Mills, as well as a Kodak marketing consideration. The Model-Client Date Cards Series consist of index cards of models used by the various clients. The Overscale Talent Releases Series include routine legal contracts which list the terms of agreement between the client, talent and the J. Walter Thompson Company. They specify the length of the contract, the client and the date. The bulk of the contracts are in their original format and therefore have actual signatures of the talent. Overscale refers to the fact that these contracts remunerated above normal union scale wages.
The Model Releases are arranged alphabetically by client and then by model and date. The Photographers files are arranged alphabetically by photographer and then by client and date. The Publications are arranged alphabetically by client and then by the name of the publication and date. Reports are arranged by client. The Model-Client index cards are arranged alphabetically by model in the first two boxes and by client (Kodak only) in the third box. The Overscale Talent Releases are arranged alphabetically by client, then by the talent name and then by date.
Restrictions on Access: Materials may not be photocopied.
Separated Material
Correspondence, mundane visuals and releases, and advertisements were removed from the collection. The advertisements were relocated in RG 10 Proof Collection. Drafts of the releases and correspondence pertaining to the releases have been removed from the collection. [Per JWT Archivist notes prior to the transfer of records to Duke University.]
Subject Headings
J. Walter Thompson Company; Chesebrough-Pond's.; Cocheco Manufacturing Company; Eastman Kodak Company; Ford Motor Company; Gillette Company; Lever Brothers and Unilever, ltd; Pan American World Airways, Inc.; Quaker Oats Company; Radio Corporation of America; Seven-Up Company; Singer Company; Uncle Ben's, Inc.; United States Lines Company; Avedon, Richard; Bartholomew, Ralph, 1907-1985; Breuhl, Anton, 1900-; Horst, 1906-1999; Mayo, Otto; Sarra, Valentino, 1903-; Scavullo, Francesco, 1921-2004; Advertising agencies -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Advertising -- Photographers; Legal forms; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History
Related Material
Related materials may be found in the following Hartman Center collections of the J. Walter Thompson Company Archives:
Advertising Vertical Files
Corporate Documentation
Domestic Advertisements Collection
Sidney Ralph Bernstein Company History Files
John F. Devine Papers
Dan Seymour Papers
Edward G. Wilson Papers
Contents of Collection
- Model Releases, 1940-1966, 16 boxes
  Consists of photographs and photostats of models as they often appeared in an advertisement. Attached to the images is a signed release by the model. The model releases are arranged alphabetically by client and then by model and date.
  - Alexander Smith, 1954, 1957 (Box 1)
  - Aquascutum (Box 1)
    - Archie Campbell, 1957 (Box 1)
    - Major Wylie, 1955 (Box 1)
  - Ballantine, 1954, (5 folders) (Box 1)
  - Burroughs Adding Machine (Box 1)
    - Fernando Arias, 1956 (Box 1)
  - Chesebrough Pond's, 1927-1959, (7 folders) (Box 2)
  - Chesebrough Pond's, 1927-1959 (continued), (10 folders) (Box 3)
  - Chesebrough Pond's, 1927-1959 (continued), (11 folders) (Box 4)
  - Ford, 1953-1964, (8 folders) (Box 5)
  - Lever Brothers, Lux, 1954-1973, (6 folders) (Box 6)
  - Lever Brothers, Lux, 1954-1973 (continued), (7 folders) (Box 7)
  - Lever Brothers, Lux, 1954-1973 (continued), (9 folders) (Box 8)
  - Lever Brothers, Lux, 1954-1973 (continued), (12 folders) (Box 9)
  - Lever Brothers, Lux, 1954-1973 (continued), (9 folders) (Box 10)
  - Lever Brothers, Lux, 1954-1973 (continued), (8 folders) (Box 11)
  - Liebman Breweries, Inc., 1962-1963 (Box 12)
  - Oneida (Box 12)
    - Donald W. Douglas, Jr., 1957 (Box 12)
    - Allen B. DuMont, 1957 (Box 12)
    - Richard Halliday, 1958 (Box 12)
    - Bob Hope, 1957 (Box 12)
    - Art Linkletter, 1958 (Box 12)
  - Pacific Mills, 1946-1955, (6 folders) (Box 12)
  - Pharma-Craft Corporation, 1952-1954, (3 folders) (Box 12)
  - Prince Matchabelli (Box 12)
    - Carroll Morrow, Jr., 1963-1964 (Box 12)
  - Pro-phy-lac-tic Brush Co., 1962 (Box 12)
  - RCA (Box 12)
    - Pearl S. Buck, 1965 (Box 12)
    - Erich Leinsdorf, 1965 (Box 12)
    - Mary Martin, 1965 (Box 12)
    - Otto Preminger, 1966 (Box 12)
  - Radio Free Europe, 1950-1956 (Box 12)
  - Religion in American Life (Box 12)
    - Norman Rockwell, 1965 (Box 12)
  - United Church Canvas, 1952-1954 (Box 12)
  - U.S. Brewers (Box 12)
    - Donald O'Connor, Mitzi Gaynor, 1960 (Box 12)
    - Esther Williams, 1960 (Box 12)
  - U.S. Lines, 1951-1963, (7 folders) (Box 13)
  - U.S. Lines, 1951-1963 (continued), (7 folders) (Box 14)
  - U.S. Lines, 1951-1963 (continued), (8 folders) (Box 15)
  - United States Treasury, 1952-1954 (Box 16)
  - Webb Young Trader, 1946-1947 (Box 16)
  - J.B. Williams Co., 1940-1952 (Box 16)
- Photographers, 1953-1967, 1 box (Box 16)
  Contains photographs and photostats of models as they often appeared in advertisements. Attached to these images are signed releases by models. Items are arranged alphabetically by photographer and then by client and date.
  - Richard Avedon (Box 2)
    - Champion Spark Plugs, 1956 (Box 2)
    - Chesebrough Pond's, 1965-1966 (Box 2)
    - Ford, 1957-1958 (Box 2)
    - Owens Illinois Glass, circa1966 (Box 2)
    - Pacific Mills, 1955-1956, (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Singer, 1966 (Box 2)
  - Ralph Bartholomew (Box 2)
    - Brillo, 1953-1954, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Anton Bruehl (Box 2)
    - Ballantine, 1954 (Box 2)
    - R.T. French, 1956 (Box 2)
    - J.B. Williams Co., 1955 (Box 2)
  - Horst P. Horst (Box 2)
    - Chesebrough-Pond's, 1964 (Box 2)
    - Fieldcrest, 1956 (Box 2)
    - Lever Brothers, 1953 (Box 2)
    - Pacific Mills, 1953 (Box 2)
    - Scott Paper, 1958 (Box 2)
    - Singer, 1964-1965 (Box 2)
    - J.B. Williams Co., 1956-1957 (Box 2)
    - Wool Bureau, 1956, 1958 (Box 2)
  - Otto Maya (Box 2)
    - Pacific Mills, 1955 (Box 2)
  - Valentino Sarra (Box 2)
    - Lever Brothers, 1953 (Box 2)
    - Institute of Life Insurance, circa 1950s (Box 2)
  - Francesco Scavullo (Box 2)
    - Chesebrough-Pond's, 1965 (Box 2)
    - Pacific Mills, 1954-55, (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Pan Am, 1967 (Box 2)
    - Burlington, 1956 (Box 2)
    - Wool Bureau, 1958 (Box 2)
  - Harry Watts (Box 2)
    - Alexander Smith, 1954 (Box 2)
- Publications, 1953-1970, 1 box (Box 2)
  Contains an assortment of publications which required model releases, and especially Ford newsletters from the 1950s. The materials are arranged alphabetically by client and then by the name of the publication and date.
  - Citizen's Committee (Box 18)
    - March...March...March...The Fifth Year of the March, 1959-1960 (Box 18)
    - Annual report, 1960-1961 (Box 18)
  - Ford (Box 18)
    - Clues, 1955-1966, (9 folders) (Box 18)
    - Buyer's Digest, 1960-1966, (4 folders) (Box 18)
    - Facts, 1956-1960, (5 folders) (Box 18)
    - Ford News Flash, 1959-1960, (2 folders) (Box 18)
    - Ford Owner Newsletter, 1963-1965, (3 folders) (Box 18)
    - Ford Truck Times, 1970 (Box 18)
  - U.S. Brewer's Foundation (Box 18)
    - ABC of Beer Advertising, 1953 (Box 18)
- Reports, 1949-1953, 1970, 1 box (Box 18)
  Consists of two folders relating to JWT clients Pacific Mills and Kodak. The Pacific Mills folder contains files related to the introduction of contour sheets from the years 1949-1953. The Kodak folder details a marketing consideration from 1970. The folders were arranged alphabetically by client.
  - Kodak, Sid Olson, 1970 (Box 19)
  - Pacific Mills, reports, 1949-1953 (Box 19)
- Model-Client-Date Cards, 1936-1949, 3 boxes (Box 19)
  Series includes three black boxes with index cards of models used by the various clients. Items are arranged alphabetically by model in the first two boxes and by client (Kodak only) in the third box.
  - Abbott, Ruth--Hylan, James (Box 20)
  - Ibsen, Leonore--Szore, Joseph (Box 21)
  - Taconelli, Sergio Cavalla--Zwill, Adrianna (Kodak only), 1943-1949 (Box 22)
- Overscale Talent Releases,1959-1978, 3 boxes (Box 22)
  Includes routine legal contracts which list the terms of agreement between the client, talent and the J. Walter Thompson Company. They specify the length of the contract, the client and the date. The bulk of the contracts are in their original format and therefore have actual signatures of the talent. Overscale refers to the fact that these contracts remunerated above normal union scale wages.
  - Brillo (Box 23)
    - Arnold Stang, 1965 (Box 23)
  - Burger King (Box 23)
    - Phyllis Hyman, 1977 (Box 23)
  - Champion Spark Plug (Box 23)
    - Tom Bosley, 1976 (Box 23)
    - Roger Maris, 1969 (Box 23)
    - Pat Summerall, 1969 (Box 23)
  - Chase & Sanborn (Box 23)
    - Mr. and Mrs. McCluskey, 1970 (Box 23)
  - Congoleum (Box 23)
    - Cyril Ritchard, 1969 (Box 23)
  - Dymo Visual Stephens (Box 23)
    - Ann Flood, 1977 (Box 23)
  - Eaton (Box 23)
    - John S. Palmer (Bud), 1971, 1976 (Box 23)
  - First National City Bank (Box 23)
    - Marion Hailey, 1968 (Box 23)
    - Steve Lawrence/Edie Gorme, 1968 (Box 23)
    - Bob and Ray, 1969 (Box 23)
  - Ford (Box 23)
    - Jane Bizzell, 1971 (Box 23)
    - Rogue Brown, 1966 (Box 23)
    - Jack Christianson, 1966 (Box 23)
    - Sid Caesar, 1970 (Box 23)
    - Roy Clark, 1975 (Box 23)
    - Vic Damone, 1966-1967 (Box 23)
    - Ann Davis, 1966 (Box 23)
    - Art Devlin, 1966 (Box 23)
    - Fearsome Four, 1966 (Box 23)
    - John Fitch, 1970 (Box 23)
    - Ernie Ford, 1966 (Box 23)
    - Walt Frazier, 1970 (Box 23)
    - Jim Gibbons, 1966 (Box 23)
    - Harry Gilmar, 1966 (Box 23)
    - Buddy Greco, 1966 (Box 23)
    - Merle Haggard, 1976-1978 (Box 23)
    - Ron Kramer, 1966 (Box 23)
    - J.P. McCarthy, 1970 (Box 23)
    - Louis Nye, 1966 (Box 23)
    - Milt Plum, 1966 (Box 23)
    - Gene Rayburn, 1969 (Box 23)
    - Tom Ryan, 1976 (Box 23)
    - Chris Schenkel, 1963 (Box 23)
    - Serendipity Singers, 1966 (Box 23)
    - Jackie Stewart, 1978 (Box 23)
    - Wayne Walker, 1966 (Box 23)
    - Tommy Watkins, 1966 (Box 23)
    - James Whitmore, 1970 (Box 23)
    - Tammy Wynette, 1975-1976 (Box 23)
  - Gillette (Box 23)
    - Henry Aaron, 1970 (Box 23)
    - Alou Bros., 1972 (Box 23)
    - Robert Bonds, 1971 (Box 23)
    - John Brodie, 1970 (Box 23)
    - Lenny Dawson, 1970 (Box 23)
    - Tom Gorman, 1972 (Box 23)
    - Ray Hodges, 1972 (Box 23)
    - Calvin Murphy, 1972 (Box 23)
    - Tony Oliva, 1972 (Box 23)
    - Jersey Joe Wolcott, 1972 (Box 23)
  - Theodore Hamm Brewing Co. (Box 23)
    - Rocky Graziano, 1969-1970 (Box 23)
    - Sugar Ray Robinson, 1969-1970 (Box 23)
  - Institute of Life Insurance (Box 23)
    - Byron Carlson, 1965-1966 (Box 23)
  - Irving Trust (Box 23)
    - Alfred Drake, 1970 (Box 23)
  - Kodak (Box 24)
    - Don Adams, 1978 (Box 24)
    - Joanna Barnes, 1971 (Box 24)
    - George Burns, 1976 (Box 24)
    - Vicki Carr, 1977 (Box 24)
    - John Forsythe, 1971 (Box 24)
    - Burl Ives, 1977 (Box 24)
    - Peggy Lee, 1975 (Box 24)
    - Art Linkletter, 1969 (Box 24)
    - Janet Lynn, 1974 (Box 24)
    - Barry Manilow, 1975 (Box 24)
    - Elizabeth Montgomery, 1969 (Box 24)
    - Louis Nye, 1970 (Box 24)
    - Jesse Owens, 1972 (Box 24)
    - Vic Perry, 1972 (Box 24)
    - Carl Reiner, 1971-1972 (Box 24)
    - Don Scardino, 1977 (Box 24)
    - Spinners, 1975 (Box 24)
    - Burr Tillstrom, 1971 (Box 24)
    - Dick Van Dyke, 1970-1972 (Box 24)
  - Lever Brothers (Box 24)
    - Jane Fonda, 1965 (Box 24)
    - Patsy Kelly, 1978 (Box 24)
    - Cheryl Ladd, 1977 (Box 24)
    - Gillis McGill, 1965 (Box 24)
    - Betsy Palmer, 1971 (Box 24)
    - Pamela Powell, 1972 (Box 24)
    - Debbie Reynolds, 1964 (Box 24)
    - Sharon Tate, 1966 (Box 24)
  - Libby, McNeill & Libby (Box 24)
    - Tony Randall, 1969 (Box 24)
  - Liggett & Myers, 1964-1966 (Box 24)
    - Eva Gabor, 1964-1966 (Box 24)
    - David Madden, 1966-1967 (Box 24)
    - Wayne Tippit, 1966-1967 (Box 24)
  - Manufacturers National Bank of Detroit (Box 25)
    - Dom de Louise, 1970 (Box 25)
  - Miles Labs (Box 25)
    - Mel Blanc, 1971 (Box 25)
    - John Carradine, 1969 (Box 25)
    - Peggy Fleming, 1970 (Box 25)
    - Patrick Fox, 1969 (Box 25)
    - Peter Graves, 1976 (Box 25)
    - Shari Lewis, 1972 (Box 25)
    - Ed Reimers, 1968 (Box 25)
    - Michael Rives, 1969 (Box 25)
  - Monroe Auto (Box 25)
    - Dick Weber, 1975 (Box 25)
  - Pan Am (Box 25)
    - Jon Charles Castaga, 1967 (Box 25)
    - Henry Clive, 1967 (Box 25)
    - Geary Decker, 1966 (Box 25)
    - Susan Dougherty, 1967 (Box 25)
    - Jim Galbraith, 1966-1967 (Box 25)
    - Elizabeth Josephson, 1967 (Box 25)
    - Robert Lamouroux, 1967 (Box 25)
    - Virginia and William Lock, 1960-1964 (Box 25)
    - Janice Pennington, 1966 (Box 25)
    - Annabel Popovic, 1966-1967 (Box 25)
    - Joe E. Roxx, 1966 (Box 25)
    - Society of Seven, 1969 (Box 25)
    - Cathy Steele, 1967 (Box 25)
  - Phillips Petroleum (Box 25)
    - Mel Allen, 1972 (Box 25)
    - Johnny Bench, 1971 (Box 25)
    - Joe Garagiola, 1968 (Box 25)
    - Curt Gowdy, 1968 (Box 25)
    - Gale Sayers, 1970 (Box 25)
    - Tom and Nancy Seaver, 1970 (Box 25)
  - Quaker Oats (Box 25)
    - Tom Ewell, 1969 (Box 25)
  - RCA (Box 25)
    - Don Adams, 1968 (Box 25)
    - Bruce Gordon, 1969 (Box 25)
    - David Huddleston, 1976 (Box 25)
    - Ted Lewis, 1968 (Box 25)
    - Vaughn Monroe, 1969 (Box 25)
    - Greg Morris, 1969 (Box 25)
    - Cyril Ritchard, 1969 (Box 25)
  - Reader's Digest (Box 25)
    - Danny Thomas, 1978 (Box 25)
  - R.J. Reynolds (Box 25)
    - Stephen Scott, 1970 (Box 25)
    - Myra Waldo, 1972 (Box 25)
  - Scott Paper (Box 25)
    - Kristina Holland, 1970 (Box 25)
    - Jenna McMahon, Richard Clau, 1967 (Box 25)
    - Carol Morley, 1975 (Box 25)
    - Mae Questel, 1972 (Box 25)
  - Seven-Up (Box 25)
    - Irwin Corey, 1968 (Box 25)
    - Geoffrey Holder, 1970 (Box 25)
    - Gary Middlecoff, 1966 (Box 25)
  - Singer (Box 25)
    - Don Ho, 1967 (Box 25)
  - Standard Brands (Box 25)
    - Kate Smith, 1969-1970 (Box 25)
  - Squibb Beech-Nut (Box 25)
    - Orson Bean, 1971 (Box 25)
  - Uncle Ben's (Box 25)
    - Ed McMahon, 1969-1971 (Box 25)
  - U.S. Marines (Box 25)
    - Christopher George, 1976 (Box 25)
  - Warner-Lambert (Box 25)
    - Jeanne Evert, 1978 (Box 25)
    - Clint Howard, 1978 (Box 25)
    - Y.A. Tittle, 1966 (Box 25)
    - William Wyndom, 1970 (Box 25)
  - Water Pik (Box 25)
    - Robert Fuller, 1976 (Box 25)
  - Whitehall Pharmaceuticals (Box 25)
    - Warren Hull, 1966 (Box 25)
  - W.F. Young (Box 25)
    - Don McNeill, 1972 (Box 25)
    - Don Wilson, 1969 (Box 25)